<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blosc Main Blog Page  (Posts about sponsorhip)</title><link>http://blosc.org/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://blosc.org/categories/sponsorhip.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:blosc@blosc.org"&gt;The Blosc Developers&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Mar 2021 18:33:50 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Seeking Sponsorship for Bcolz/Blosc</title><link>http://blosc.org/posts/seeking-sponsoship/</link><dc:creator>Valentin Haenel</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dear Everyone,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;as you may or may not know, the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/blosc/c-blosc"&gt;Blosc&lt;/a&gt;
compressor has become the basis for some novel, innovative technological
experiments in the PyData space.  Especially the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/blosc/bcolz"&gt;Bcolz&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/blosc/bloscpack"&gt;Bloscpack&lt;/a&gt; projects which provide a way to perform
out-of-core computations on column based datasets have become particularly
interesting for the analysis of medium-sized time-series datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, we would like to convince you to give us some money to
foster the project, development and accelerate growth of our community.
Historically, it has always been a difficult endeavour to monetize
open-source development and so, below is a non-exhaustive list of
potential models that we are considering:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Direct sponsoring / Donations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This involves paying either a single lump-sum or monthly installments
to foster continued development and innovation. This type of
sponsoring isn't bound to any specific goal or feature and would allow
us for example maintain and release the projects regularly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Feature-driven sponsoring&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paying for specific features to be implemented, bugs to be fixed or
paying to have a voice when it comes to prioritizing items in the
issue-tracker(s).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hiring us as freelancers for Blosc/Bcolz projects&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that you hire one or both of us to implement a project that
uses bcolz inside your company. Any bugs we find or improvements that
need to be made would flow back into the open source code-base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hiring us as part-time freelancers for general projects&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means you hire one or both of us as part-time freelancers for two
to three days a week to work on general projects. These can be related
to Python and data or open-source work on other projects. This would
allow us to spend the remaining days on Blosc/Bcolz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;PhD positions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still a few interesting theoretical aspects to be unlocked,
for example certain mathematical properties of the shuffle filter and
a compressed extension of the external-memory-model (EMM) to analyse
the runtime of Blosc style out-of-core algorithms and Bcolz operations
in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We welcome any feedback regarding the above options and please do tell
us about any additional models that may be interesting to us or for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With best wishes and looking forward to your input,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Francesc Alted and Valentin Haenel&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>blosc</category><category>blosclz</category><category>sponsorhip</category><guid>http://blosc.org/posts/seeking-sponsoship/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 26 May 2015 08:41:20 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>